Register of the Ardashīr Zāhidī papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ardashīr Zāhidī papers
1915-2014
(Bulk, 1973-1979)
2009C59
Hoover Institution Archives
273 manuscript boxes, 75 oversize boxes, 924 computer files (1.6 GB) (226.4 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, interview transcripts, financial records, photographs, video and sound recordings, printed matter, and computer disks relating to Ardeshir Zahedi's diplomatic career during the Pahlavi era in Iran. Zahedi served as Ambassador to the United States, Ambassador to the United Kingdom, and as Minister of Foreign Affairs during the reign of Mohammad Reza Pahlavi. The collection also contains the papers of Ardeshir's father, Fazlollah Zahedi, a general who occupied the post of prime minister. Topics of note include: Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, Iranian foreign relations, Iranian-American relations, the Cold War, the events of August 1953, the 1977 Hanafi Siege, and Iranian dissent.
Zāhidī, Ardashīr, 1928-
Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2009, with an additional increment received in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Ardeshir Zahedi (Ardashīr Zāhidī) was an Iranian statesman and diplomat during Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi's reign (1941-1979). He was born in 1928 to Fazlollah Zahedi and Khadijeh Pirnia, who both stemmed from significant political backgrounds.
Fazlollah Zahedi, one of the generals who overthrew Mohammed Mossadegh in 1953, occupied the post of prime minister from 1953 to 1955. Prior to that, Fazlollah Zahedi had a significant military and political career, participating in military campaigns such as the suppression of the Jangal movement and the arrest of Sheikh Kha’zal Khan. During World War II, he was interned by the British in Palestine from 1941 to 1945, under the allegation of collaborating with German forces. After his internment, Fazlollah Zahedi held posts of Chief of National Police and Minister of Interior. Meanwhile, Ardeshir obtained his Bachelor of Science from Utah State University in 1950, and worked for the Point Four Program upon his return to Iran. Both Ardeshir and Fazlollah Zahedi found themselves at odds with the Mossadegh government, and during the turbulent events of August 1953, Ardeshir Zahedi stayed close to his father’s side. These events, known as the 28 Mordad coup, resulted in the overthrow of Mossadegh and the appointment of Fazlollah Zahedi as Prime Minister. However, Fazlollah Zahedi’s term was short-lived, as he was forced to resign in 1955. He was then appointed Ambassador to the United Nations in Geneva, and lived in Switzerland until his death in 1963. Ardeshir Zahedi maintained close relations with the Shah, and married his eldest daughter, Shahnaz Pahlavi, in 1957. They had one child, Mahnaz Zahedi, and divorced in 1964. Ardeshir Zahedi held his first diplomatic post in the United States from 1959 to 1961, and was then appointed Ambassador to the United Kingdom from 1962 to 1966. From 1966 to 1971 he served as Minister of Foreign Affairs. Ardeshir Zahedi was appointed Ambassador to the United States a second time in 1973, and occupied this position until the Iranian Revolution forced the Shah from power in 1979. Ardeshir Zahedi tried to find political asylum for the Shah and his family, and was present for his death and funeral in Cairo. In the wake of Iran’s transformation from a monarchy to an Islamic republic, Ardeshir Zahedi has resided in Montreux, Switzerland, occasionally providing interviews and commentary on Iranian politics. He has spent the last several years working on his memoirs, a multi-volume project.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Ardashīr Zāhidī papers contain correspondence, speeches and writings, interview transcripts, financial records, photographs, video and sound recordings, printed matter, and computer disks relating to Ardeshir Zahedi's diplomatic career during the Pahlavi era. Zahedi served as Ambassador to the United States, Ambassador to the United Kingdom, and as Minister of Foreign Affairs during the reign of Mohammad Reza Pahlavi. The collection also contains the papers of Ardeshir's father, Fazlollah Zahedi, a general who occupied the post of prime minister. Topics of note include: Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, Iranian foreign relations, Iranian-American relations, the Cold War, the events of August 1953, the 1977 Hanafi Siege, and Iranian dissent.
The Faz̤l Allāh Zāhidī Papers document Fazlollah's military and political career, his internment in Palestine during World War II, his tenure as prime minister, and his appointment as diplomat to the United Nations in Geneva. They also contain materials related to Ardeshir's youth and marriage.
The Minister of Foreign Affairs File includes correspondence, transcripts, notes, and reports related to meetings with foreign officials, dignitaries, and heads of state.
Ardeshir's second appointment as Ambassador to the United States spanned the presidencies of Richard Nixon, Gerald Ford, and Jimmy Carter, and ended with the Shah's abdication. The Ambassador to the United States File documents this period and includes embassy documents and Ardeshir's correspondence. Ardeshir corresponded with a wide range of people, including U.S. and Iranian government officials, and members of the press.
Since resigning from his diplomatic post, Ardeshir has resided in Montreux, Switzerland. The Career after Diplomacy File demonstrates his engagement in editing and providing resources for works about the Pahlavi era, drafts and documents compiled for his memoirs, and editorial and interview materials.
The Photographs series includes photographs and albums from Fazlollah's youth through Ardeshir's second appointment in the United States. Although different stages of Ardeshir's life and career are depicted, including his wedding and his first appointment in the United States, his second appointment in the United States is the most documented aspect of his life. Other areas of interest include photographs from the 1953 coup and of the Pahlavis.
General Note
Persian names of individuals have been Romanized according to Library of Congress standards as well as common usage.
Dates mostly follow the Gregorian calendar; Iranian calendar dates are accompanied by conversions.
Diplomats--Iran.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Iran.; Iran--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Iran--Foreign relations--United States.; Iran--Foreign relations.; Iran--History--20th century.; Iran--History--Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, 1941-1979; United States--Foreign relations--Iran.
- Faz̤l Allāh Zāhidī Papers, 1923-1963
  - Biographical file, 1923-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1-3, Box 244)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes military identification document with accompanying papers, documents promoting Zahedi to "sarlashgar" and recognizing his service at Delimqan, diplomatic passport, and documents appointing him as Ambassador to the United Nations.
  - Journal, circa 1302 [1923] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Journal includes narrative and photographs depicting the capture of Mir Abbas. Photographs include Fazlollah Zahedi, Mir Abbas, Mahmoud Aram, military fortresses, and members of the Kashkuli tribe.
  - Notebooks, circa 1937-1949
    Notebooks mostly written during Fazlollah's time imprisoned by the British in Palestine during World War II. Includes accounts of military campaigns, as well as accompanying photographs and letters.
    - 1937-1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Includes loose papers and photographs.
    - 1320 [1941] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1944 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - circa 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
    - Sheikh Khaz'al mission, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Fazlollah's account of the Sheikh Khazal rebellion in Khuzestan.
  - Correspondence, circa 1928-1952
    - By person, subject, circa 1936-1946
      - Albert, Bela Laub, 1315 [1936] (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Pahlavī, Shams, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Qashqāʼī, Muḥammad Nāṣir, 1321-1325 [1942-1946] (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Zāhidī, Ardashīr, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chronological, 1928-1952
      - Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - 1306-1308 [1928-1929] (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 1928 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Correspondence chiefly with the Deutsch-Orientalische Handels-Gesellschaft.
      - 1310s [1930s] (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - 1320s [1940s] (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Correspondents include Sayyid Nasrallah Bani Sadr.
      - 1943-1945 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - 1330-1331 [1951-1952] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Other collected materials, circa 1920s-1953
    - Memos, 1325-1330 [1946-1951] (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Includes memos from the court and the Finance Ministry.
    - Notes, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Writing, 1332 Farvardīn [1953 April] (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Political declaration, possibly written or edited by Fazlollah.
    - Fars rebellion, 1325 [1946] (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Includes materials relating to the 1946 tribal rebellion, the Qashqa'i tribe, and Fazlollah's mission to Shiraz.
    - Majlis-i Sinā, circa 1951 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Photographs, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Photographs of Fazlollah and his military cohort.
  - Prime Minister files, 1953-1955
    - Notepad, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Notebook, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Includes accompanying notes, fragments, and letters.
    - Agenda, 1333 [1955] (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Notes, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      Includes draft of speech.
    - Correspondence, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1332-1333 [1953-1955] (Box 2, Folder 23)
      Correspondents include Sayyid Hasan Taqizadah.
    - Cards, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Qashqāʼī, Muḥammad Nāṣir, 1332 [1953] (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Fāṭimī, Ḥusayn, 1954 March (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Muqaddam, Muṣṭafá va Buyūk Qazvīnī, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Reports and memos, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Includes report from the Ministry of Roads and "Special Report at the Turning Point of the Special Assistance Program in Iran," 1955 January 13, and reports from Sāzmān-i Barnāmah, Vizārat-i Rāh, and Vizārat-i Iqtiṣād-i Millī.
    - Financial documents, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Photographs, circa 1953-1955 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Includes photographs of Hossein Fatemi (Ḥusayn Fāṭimī).
  - Ambassador in Switzerland, 1955-1963
    - Notepad, circa 1955-1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Chronological correspondence, 1955-1963
      Includes letters from Shaban Jafari, and letters written to Prime Minister Asadollah Alam.
      - circa 1955 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - 1334 [1955] (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
      - 1334 [1955-1956] (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - 1335 [1956-1957] (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
      - 1336 [1957-1958] (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
      - 1337 [1958-1959] (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - 1338 [1959-1960] (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
      - 1339 [1960-1961] (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - 1340-1341 [1961-1963] (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - 1342 [1963] (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence by person or organization, 1957-1963
      - Afshār, Yār, 1336-1342 [1957-1963] (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Ḥikmat, ʻAlī Aṣghar, 1337-1339 [1958-1960] (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Narāqī, Ṣādiq, 1339-1342 [1960-1963] (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Qaraguzlū, ʻAlī Riz̤ā, 1338-1340 [1959-1961] (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Qavāmī Shīrāzī, Muḥammad, 1336 [1957-1958] (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Rūznāmah-i Iṭṭilāʻāt, circa 1959 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Tājī, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Vizārat-i Umūr-i Khārijah, 1337-1342 [1958-1963] (Box 3, Folder 19)
        Correspondents include Hekmat E Shirazi (ʻAlī Aṣghar Ḥikmat) and Abbas Aram.
      - Zāhidī, Ardashīr, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence by subject, 1956-1962
      - Adl, Aḥmad Ḥusain, circa 1958 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Ash, Arthur, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Automobile-Club de Suisse, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Economic projects in Iran, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Hekmatan Sugar Company, 1337-1340 [1958-1961] (Box 3, Folder 25)
        Includes photographs of factory.
      - Lassaker, Mohamed, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Nāṣirī, Ghulām, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Pahlavi, Ashraf, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Shūrā-yi ʻĀlī-i Jamʻīyat'hā-yi Zanān-i Īrān, 1340 [1962] (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Taraqqī khavāhān-i Iran, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Telegrams, 1955-1963
      - 1955 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - 1956 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - 1957 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Other collected materials, circa 1955-1963
      - Business cards and notes, circa 1955-1963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Includes some of Ardeshir's notes.
      - Writings, circa 1955-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6, Box 257)
        Includes written answers to interview questions.
      - Namāyandagī-i Dāʼimī-i Iran dar Daftar-i Urūpāyī Sāzmān-i Milal-i Mutaḥid, 1958-1961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Financial documents from the Iranian delegation to the United Nations.
      - Financial notes, circa 1955-1963 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Photographs, circa 1956-1957 (Box 4, Folder 9)
        Includes photographs of Ardeshir, Fazlollah, and Shahnaz Pahlavi.
      - Miscellaneous, circa 1955 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Printed material, 1947-1961
    - Ephemera, circa 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 11-12, Box 235)
      Includes a poem printed on the occasion of the death of Pakistani Prime Minister Liaquat Ali Khan, political fliers related to Fazlollah and Ardeshir's role in the events of August 1953, and a booklet from the Imperial Embassy of Iran, Bern.
    - Clippings, 1952-1958
      Mostly about Ardeshir and Shahnaz Pahlavi's wedding, Fazlollah, and the events of August 1953. In French, German, and Persian.
      - 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
      - 1331-1337 [1952-1958] (Box 4, Folder 15-22, Box 5, Folder 1-12)
    - Newspapers, 1955-1961
      - Ārzū-yi shumāl, 1334 Murdād 28 [1955 August 20] (Box 5, Folder 13)
        Shumārah-i 140, sāl-i 4.
      - Ātash, Urdībihisht 20 [May 10] (Box 5, Folder 14)
        Shumārah-i 1633.
      - Āzhang, Urdībihisht 15 [May 5] (Box 5, Folder 15)
        Shumārah-i 49, sāl-i 4.
      - Dunyā, 1334 Bahman 1-8 [1956 January 22-29] (Box 5, Folder 16)
        Shumārah-i 391, sāl-i 11.
      - Īrān-i bāstān, 1339 Murdād [1960 August] (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - Ittiḥād-i millī, 1335 Murdād 9 [1956 July 31] (Box 5, Folder 18)
        Shumārah-i 427, sāl-i 12.
      - Iṭṭilāʻāt, Iṭṭilāʻāt-i havāʼī, 1334-1340 [1955-1961] (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Javan mardān, 1334 [1955] (Box 5, Folder 20)
        Shumārah-i 335.
      - Kayhān, 1334 [1955] (Box 5, Folder 21)
        Shumārah-i 3620, 3639, sāl-i 14.
      - Muzākarāt-i Majlis-i Shawrā-yi Millī, 1334-1335 [1955-1957] (Box 235)
      - Muzākarāt-i Majlis-i Sinā, 1334-1335 [1955-1957] (Box 235)
      - Pust-i Tihrān, 1334 Murdād 16 [1955 August 8] (Box 5, Folder 22)
        Shumārah-i 653, sāl-i 2.
      - Ṣadā-yi vaṭan, 1334 Khurdād-Murdād [1955 June-August] (Box 5, Folder 23)
        Shumārah-i 576, 586, sāl-i 12.
      - Shīr nishān, 1331-1334 [1952-1955] (Box 5, Folder 24)
        Shumārah-i 10 sāl-i avval; shumārah-i 19, 20, 21 sāl-i duvvum; shumārah-i 57, 59, 60, 82 sāl-i sivvum; shumārah-i 89, 91, 108 sāl-i chahārum.
      - Spanish and German publications, 1957 November (Box 235, 257)
      - Ṭūfan-i Sharq, 1334 Tīr 3 [1955 June 25] (Box 235)
    - Shahnaz Pahlavi's stationery, circa 1957-1963 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Books, 1947-1957
      - Ḥuqūq, undated (Box 6)
      - Kitāb-i zanāshuvī-yi dar Islām, 1326 Ābān [1947 November] (Box 6)
      - Naft, 1336 Tīr [1957 July] (Box 6)
      - Qurʼān Majīd, 1329 [1950] (Box 6)
      - Furūghī Basṭāmī. Dīvān-i Kāmil-i Furūghī Basṭāmī: bi-khaṭṭ-i Kalhur. Tihrān: Az Intishārāt-i ʻAbd al-Raḥmān Sayf Āzād, 1957 (Box 6)
      - Khvājah Nūrī, Ibrāhīm. ʻAqāyid-i Lalah Āqā yā makātīb-i haftagī. [Tehran]: Chapkhanah-i Masʻud Saʼd, 1334 [1955] (Box 6)
        Jild-i savvum.
      - Junge, Peter Julius, and Davoud Monchi-Zadeh. Dāriyūsh-i yakum pādishāh-i pārs'hā. Tihrān: Dānishgāh-i Tihrān, 1956 (Box 6)
      - Jamālzādah, Muḥammad ʻAlī. Ganj-i shāyagān, yā, Awz̤āʻ-i iqtiṣādī-i Īrān. Birlīn: Kāvīyānī, 1956 (Box 6)
      - Muʻīniyān, Nuṣrat Allāh. Qiyām dar rāh-i salṭanat, 9 Isfand 1331-28 Murdād 1332. Chapkhanah-i Majlis. (Box 6)
      - Qadīmī, Aḥmad Riz̤ā. Zindagānī-yi ḥaz̤rat Muḥammad. Tihrān: Chāpkhānah Maẓaharī, 1958 (Box 6)
      - Schaeder, Hans Heinrich. Jahāndārī-i Pars'hā. Tihrān: Intishārāt-i Farhang-i Sūmkā, 1335 [1956] (Box 6)
- Minister of Foreign Affairs File, 1965-1971
  Includes meeting transcripts and notes, reports, talking points, memoranda, correspondence, shared statements between countries, speeches, and financial records. Subjects include Middle East politics, the Persian Gulf, disputed territories in the Persian Gulf, the Arab-Israeli Conflict, communism and the Soviet Union, arms, oil, and Iran's military and economic relations. Materials are largely in Persian, with some documents in Arabic, English, French, and German.
  Arranged according to orginal order.
  - Inventory of files, circa 1970 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Reports reviewed by the Shah year 1345, 1966-1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Talks between the Shah and the President of Turkey, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Talks between the Foreign Ministers of Iran and Turkey, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Notes on dicussions between Zahedi and İhsan Sabri Çağlayangil regarding foreign relations in the Middle East, with Pakistan and the United States, communism, and Iran's purchase of arms from the Soviet Union.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of Turkey, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Foreign Minister of Iran with the President and the Foreign Minister of Czechoslovakia, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Meetings in New York, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    Includes notes from discussions with Dean Rusk, Joseph J. Sisco, Hubert Humphrey, Stuart W. Rockwell, Eugene V. Rostow, the Foreign Ministers of England and Turkey, the United States Secretary of State, and the Ambassador of Pakistan.
  - Discussions with Goronwy Roberts, Minister of State for Foreign Affairs, 1965-1967 (Box 235, Box 7, Folder 11-15)
    Subjects include the Arab-Israeli Conflict, the Persian Gulf, Yemen, the Federation of South Arabia, Iraq, Central Treaty Organization (CENTO), and oil. Includes notes and subject information from Roberts's visit to Iran, summaries of meetings from previous folder, communications between Zahedi and Abbas Aram, communications with the Department of Code, the Iranian Embassy in Baghdad, and the Iraqi Embassy in Tehran.
  - Talks with the Emir of Kuwait, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Talks between the Shah and Goronwy Roberts, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Talks between Iranian and British representatives on the Persian Gulf, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 18-21)
  - Talks between the Shah and the President of Turkey, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Travels to France, England, and America, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    Includes notes, talking points, and a few letters.
  - Meetings in Paris, London, and Washington D.C., 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    Includes notes from discussions between Zahedi and George Brown, British Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and Dean Rusk, United States Secretary of State.
  - Reports reviewed by the Shah year 1346, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    Includes reports and memos from Zahedi to the Shah, letters to Zahedi, and a draft for the Shah's speech on Regional Cooperation for Development.
  - Reports reviewed by the Shah years 1347-1348, 1968-1970 (Box 8, Folder 7-11)
    Includes reports and memos from Zahedi to the Shah, and communications between Zahedi and Asadalloh Alam.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of Iran with Alexei Kosygin, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 12-13)
  - Talks between the King of Morocco, the Prime Minister of Iran, and the Minister of Foreign Affairs of Iran, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Talks between the Foreign Ministers of Great Britain and Iran in London, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Topics include the Persian Gulf and Middle Eastern countries.
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of Iran with Marshal Tito, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    Other participants include Koča Popović and Amir Khosrow Afshar. Subjects include Arab countries, Arab-Israeli relations, and Vietnam.
  - Talks between the Shah and the President of Turkey, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Talks between the Prime Minister of Iran and the President of Poland, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Talks between the Shah and the Prime Minister of France, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Transciption from meetings with the Shah, George Pompidou, Amir-Abbas Hoveyda, and Zahedi, largely on economic issues.
  - Meetings in Hungary, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    Includes notes and meeting transcripts from discussions with Pál Losonczi, Chairman of the Presidential Council, and Prime Minister Jenő Fock.
  - Talks between the Shah and the President of Poland, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    Includes transcripts from talks between the Shah and Marian Spychalski, Chairman of the Council of State.
  - Amīr Khusraw Afshār, 1968-1969 (Box 9, Folder 1-4, Box 8, Folder 22)
    Includes transcripts from discussions between Amir Khosrow Afshar and the Soviet Ambassador; Afshar and the Deputy Secretary for the Arab League; communications between Afshar, Zahedi, Ahmed Tehrani, and Jahanbani; and reports from Afshar to Zahedi regarding other negotiations with England and the United States. Topics include other Middle Eastern countries, as well as Pakistan and China.
  - Iran and Kuwait, 1965-1968 (Box 9, Folder 5-9)
    Includes notes from state visit discussions; schedules from state visits of the Emir of Kuwait to Iran; reports from the National Iranian Oil Company, the Iranian Embassy in Kuwait, the Department of Code, and other governmental departments, and reports on various issues related to Iran-Kuwait relations including visas to Kuwait and Iranian workers in Kuwait, fishing in the Persian Gulf, and the naming of the Persian Gulf; communications with the Kuwait Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Iranian Foreign Affairs, and the Department of Housing and Urban Development; and texts from treaties and agreements between Iran and Kuwait.
  - Ramsar Conference records, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 10-13)